<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="no"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"  category="info" docName="draft-hegde-lsr-ospf-better-idbx"
     ipr="trust200902"
     obsoletes="" submissionType="IETF" updates="" xml:lang="en">
    <front>
        <title abbrev="draft-hegde-lsr-ospf-better-idbx">
            Trusted Domain SRv6
        </title>

        <author fullname="Shraddha Hegde" initials="S." surname="Hegde">
            <organization>Juniper</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>
                    </street>
                    <city></city>
                    <region>
                    </region>
                    <code/>
                    <country>India
                    </country>
                </postal>
                <phone/>
                <facsimile/>
                <email>shraddha@juniper.net
                </email>
                <uri/>
            </address>
        </author>
         <author fullname="Tony Przygienda" initials="A." surname="Przygienda">
            <organization>Juniper</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>1133 Innovation Way
                    </street>
                    <city>Sunnyvale</city>
                    <region>CA
                    </region>
                    <code/>
                    <country>USA
                    </country>
                </postal>
                <phone/>
                <facsimile/>
                <email>prz@juniper.net
                </email>
                <uri/>
            </address>
        </author>
         <author fullname="Acee Lindem" initials="A." surname="Lindem">
            <organization>LabN Consulting LLC</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                  <street>
                    301 Midenhall Way
                  </street>
                  <city>Cary</city>
                  <region>
                    North Carolina
                  </region>
                  <code/>
                  <country>
                    USA
                  </country>
                </postal>
                <phone/>
                <facsimile/>
                <email>acee.ietf@gmail.com
                </email>
                <uri/>
            </address>
        </author>
         
        <date year="2023"/>
        <abstract>
            <t>
                 When an OSPF router undergoes restart, previous instances LSAs belonging to that router
                 may still linger in the databases of other routers in the OSPF domain until such LSAs are aged out.
                Hence, when the restarting
                 router joins the network again, neighboring routers re-establish adjacencies while the
                 restarting router is still bringing-up its interfaces and adjacencies and generates LSAs with
                 sequence numbers that may be lower than the stale LSAs. Such stale LSAs may be interpreted as bi-directional
                 connectivity before the initial database exchanges are finished and genuine bi-directional LSA
                 connectivity exists.
                 Such incorrect interpretation may lead to, among other thigs, transient traffic unreachability.
                 This document suggests improvements in the OSPF database exchange
                 process to prevent such problems due to stale LSA utilization. The solution does not preclude
                 changes in the existing standard but presents an extension that will prevent this scenario.
            </t>
        </abstract>
        <note title="Requirements Language">
          <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
          NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
          "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
          described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119" format="default"/> <xref target="RFC8174" format="default"/>
          when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
        </note>
    </front>
    <middle>


        <section title="Introduction" anchor='sec_introduction'>        
            <t>
               When an OSPF <xref target ='RFC2328'/> router restarts, its stale LSAs are left in the
               database of other  routers in the OSPF domain until the LSAs are aged out either
               intentionally or by the LSA age elasping. The stale
               Router LSA can contain links to all the neighbors that had adjacencies Up before the router
               restarted.
                 <figure anchor="Topology_1" title="OSPF Network">
                 <artwork>
                            ----------C--------
                            |                 |
                      A-----B                 E-----F
                            |                 |
                            --------D---------                   
                      
                      
                 </artwork> 
                 </figure>
                 <xref target ='Topology_1'/> shows a very simple OSPF network. In case of C undergoing restart that
                 does not generate purges, the other routers
                 in the domain will hold the stale LSA of Router C in their database. The stale LSA may have
                 links to B and E, which represents the topology of C before it went down. When C restarts again,
                 it initiates the database exchange process with B and E. B and E may have C's stale LSA with a higher
                 sequence number in their database than the new ones originated by C and
                 hence assume this is latest copy, successively bringing up the adjacency
                 with C, and transitioning to Full state. Based on C's Stale LSA having LSA links to B and E,
                 the Shortest Path First (SPF) back-link check is satisfied and B and E update their routing table to point
                 to C. This may cause C to drop this traffic as C may not have all its previous adjacencies up and
                 all LSAs in place to correctly compute the necessary routes.
            </t>
        </section>
          <section title="Solution" anchor='sec_solution'>
               <t>
                    The database exchange procedure from <xref target ='RFC2328'/> section 7.2 is extended with additional
                    procedure added.</t>
                 <t>   
                    During Database exchange, when a router receives an LSA from the neighbor for which such neighbor is the originator
                    of the LSA and the sequence number of the LSA is smaller than its own database copy, the receiving router marks
                    its own database copy as stale. Router adds the newly stale LSA to the Link State Request List. 
                    Until an LSA with the sequence number greater than its own database copy is received (or strictly speaking, a "newer"
                    LSA based on usual comparison), this LSA must not be removed from the Link State Request list and the adjacency FSM
                    MUST NOT transition to Full state.</t>
               <section title="Example" anchor='sec_ex'>
                    <t>  <xref target ='seq_dgm'/> provides an example of C restarting having originated an LSA with sequence number
                         Y before. After restarting C originates the same LSA with sequence number X where X &lt; Y since
                        it is not aware of existence of version X yet.
                         <figure anchor="seq_dgm" title="Modified Database Exchange Procedure">
                         <artwork>
                             <![CDATA[
                              
          C-----------------E

      DBD: LSA A origin:C  ------->
          Sequence:X
                              DBD: LSA A Origin:C
                      <------       Sequence:Y
      LSReq LSA A,
      origin C, Seq Y----->
                            Modified Procedure
                     <------ LSReq LSA A, Origin C, Seq X
      LSA A, Origin C,
      Seq:X          ------->
                     <------- LSA  A, Origin C, Seq:Y
      C re-originating self LSA
      LSA A, Origin C, -------> Mark LSReq
      Seq:Y+1                    LSAA, Origin C, Seq X
                                  Satisfied
                                            
                         ]]>
                         </artwork>
                         </figure>
                            As shown in figure <xref target ='seq_dgm'/> above, E originates LSReq with Sequence number X but
                         waits until the LSA with sequence number Y+1 (or strictly speaking, an LSA that compares as newer
                        to the one it holds) arrives. As the LSA is still in the LSReq queue, the adjacency
                         will remain in Loading state and will not move to Full state. All the neighbors of the restarting routers 
                         hold the neighborship in Loading state and do not make it Full until the stale LSA is replaced with the new LSA
                         with higher sequence number than the stale LSA. This ensures that other routers in the network do not compute
                         a path through the restarting router since they cannot satisfy the bi-directionality condition
                        in reachability computations.
                    </t>
               </section>
          </section>

          <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations" toc="default">

            <t>
              No IANA Considerations
            </t>
          </section>

        <section title="Security Considerations">
            <t>
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Contributors">
            <t></t>
        </section>

    </middle>
    <back>
        <references title="Informative References">

        </references>
        <references title="Normative References">
            <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
            <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2328.xml"/>
            <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
           

        </references>

    </back>
</rfc>
